so we share the screen
and i'm opening the chat
all right so i have the chat open so you
can interact with me
and so a small recap from last time last
time we've been talking about energy
uh and actually we've been talking about
inference
how to find set how to find y check uh
how to compute y
f and e okay and so let me just start
i guess with the the last slide from
last time so we
had computed this f infinity uh which is
called
uh zero temperature limit uh free energy
uh as a function of my y and y is going
to be a two dimensional
vector right so whenever i'm going to be
plotting this f
infinity of y it's going to be a scalar
field means this a height
over like a 2d region okay
so we saw already this stuff that since
it's gonna have different height i'm
gonna represent with the
color purple the height equals zero
and then color equal green for
equal one and then everything that is
above and beyond
the free energy equal tool is going to
be in
yellow okay and so
this is how this stuff looks i
would like to remind you that this free
energy was the quadratic
uh a cliton distance from the model
manifold right so all points that are
within the um within the model manifold
they have zero cost right
this is sorry zero energy free energy
because again the
the distance between them and the
manifold is zero so zero squared is zero
and then as you move away it's gonna
it's gonna increase up
uh quadratically so
uh so far everything should be uh
known understood and you know you you
took yeah you had one week to to go over
this stuff so
i i assume everyone is quite familiar
so something that you may notice right
now is gonna be in the side
of these ellipse you're going to have
like a region that is slightly
slightly lighter right you can see a
lighter degree of
purple so what's going on over there so
let me show you this
uh image here uh with the height
you know proportional to the actual
height of this um
of this free energy okay so i'm gonna
change the color map such that
uh you can clearly see what's going on
and i'm gonna be using this one which is
called
cold warm so cold means like
f infinity equals zero i'm going to be
using the blue color
for f infinity equal 0.5 i'm gonna be
using
a gray color and then for everything
that is above and beyond
f infinity one is going to be in red
and so this is going to be um the the
image you saw before now that was like
simply saw from
uh from top here i'm gonna show you the
contour
so each uh line here they share the same
value of the free energy
okay so let me spin this little guy so
it's that you can see all around
as you can tell all the regions like the
height
around the the the ellipse that is
with the the manifold ellipse is gonna
have zero energy
and as you move away from that you're
gonna have like a quadratic thing right
so you're gonna have like a parabola
uh what you notice is that in the center
so on the outside of course is going to
be like a parabola but in the center
those two things are going to be going
up on a peak
right and this might
or might not be wanted and so the
this we're gonna start today lesson by
learning how to relax
this uh free energy this infinite zero
temperature limit free energy
to a more you know uh a free energy
without
local minima such that you know it's a
bit more smooth
let me take here a cross section of this
you know bathtub
for y one equals zero so i'm gonna be
chaff
chopping it in a correspondence of y one
equals zero
so what we get is going to be the
following you're gonna see now
that those two branches are gonna be my
parabolic branches right
so again what is this free energy free
energy
was the square distance of your given
point
to the closest point on the manifold
right
so if you're on the manifold which is
like location
0.4 for example then the distance
between you
and the manifold is going to be zero and
therefore the square of zero is going to
be zero
as you move away let's say we move to
the right hand side of this
0.4 as you move linearly to the right
hand side
you're going to be increasing
quadratically right that's why we
observe
this energy free energy going up
quadratically
similarly what happens on the other side
of course
the same happens as you move towards the
zero right and so as you move towards
the zero you're gonna get
that you try to climb up that parabola
and we have this peak over here and so
in the next
slide we're gonna be learning how to
smooth that peak
i'll let you i tell you later why we uh
what is very why
this is very useful like why we why my
why
we might want to do so okay
so free energy we we know right the the
minimum
value of the energy e that
is spanning across y and z right so
you have this energy we saw that uh for
a given y we have like an energy over z
and then the free energy was the value
of the energy correspondent
to the location where we have the
minimum value right so the minimum value
of this
e is going to be my free energy
now i'm going to be introducing a
relaxed version which is going to be
this uh purple f so
this purple f function parameterized by
beta
is going to be simply this expression uh
what is this beta
right so this beta it's in
physics it's called the inverse
temperature
the thermo thermodynamic inverse
temperature or the
coldness and it's simply one over
uh kb which is the boltzmann constant
multiplied by the temperature okay
so again if t that capital t the
temperature is very very very high
like it's very warm like you're on the
sun beta is gonna be
extremely small right it's gonna be zero
instead if temperature the temperature
is cold like
zero kelvin then automatically you're
gonna get that beta
it's plus infinity right and so
now you can understand why
i call my f infinity the zero
temperature limit
free energy so it's zero temperature
it's super cold right
so capital t is zero meaning beta is
plus infinity
so again if you have this free energy
with so-called free energy
the free energy is going to be exactly
the minimum otherwise if you relax
this constraint as you warm up a little
bit this free energy
the free energy is going to be a
summation of multiple
things right so this s here is the s for
sum is a summation of all these
components here multiplied by the
interval cool
this symbol over here it's simply the
measure
of the domain of z so in our case
uh z goes from zero to two pi and
therefore
this item over here it simply means two
pi
okay all right all right but who
who remembers what this kbt is right
what is this kbt why are we talking
about energies right
so again from physics no 101 you might
remember that
the average
translational kinetic energy was the two
third
kbt no and therefore kbt or two third
kbt
express the uh kinetic energy right of
this
let's say gas with all those particles
and so the temperature allows you to
express
uh the energy right so you have
temperature and energy are connected
um so you can make uh
a quick you know check check here and
beta since it's going to be the inverse
of kbt it's going to be in one over
joule right and so here we have these
one over joule means that this stuff is
joule therefore f is going to be an
energy
and then inside this exponential we have
one over
joule times the e which is joule and
then if you multiply the two you
then the two you know units cancel out
so
everything works just fine
all right all right all right um and
also yes
the the dimension of z cancel out with
this dimension right so everything is
just pure
uh pure number okay again these are this
is not machine learning this is physics
just to give you a little bit of you
know uh
overview about what this stuff where
this stuff comes from right so this is
just from our friends from the physics
department
all right all right all right so i want
to compute this free energy in this
relaxed version of this
uh free energy uh since i don't want to
compute this integral
i may not know how to do that i simply
use a simple discretization right
and so i replace this latin s with a
greek s right and then i replace this
latin d
with a greek t so everything else is
just the same so i go from the
time continuous to a discretization very
simple discretization it works
in our case because z is like one
dimension i saw you know everything is
pretty easy uh
moreover here i will just define and
pay attention i am defining right now
for this class
okay this thing uh has been the
soft mean of e so my
free energy uh the purple one
it's simply the relaxation of the zero
temperature
limit is going to be simply this soft
mean so
the zero temperature the super cold one
is simply the mean
okay am i n min whereas if i
compute if i relax if i turn on the
temperature
like i increase the thermostat i'm gonna
have this
soft mean which is this log
summation of exponential okay and i call
this actual
soft mean why do i call it actual soft
meme because other people
uh most of the people outside this class
will call this the soft means something
else and i will let you
know a bit more about these in a few
slides okay
something that is super interesting is
computing the limit of this free energy
here for beta that goes to zero so
whenever you increase the temperature
as the temperature on the sun like it's
super warm what is the most
relaxed version of this min
and so if you do that you're gonna see
that
this stuff ends up being the average but
again this is just you know
um it's not relevant it's not too
important
uh is the derivation just i can show you
here
and i just show you so you can you have
access later
uh the limit of this free energy
for beta that goes to zero so it's very
warm
super warm it ends up being simply the
average
of the energy okay across those heads
again not to uh you don't have to get
scared about that math
all right so let's compute this free
energy for
the cases we saw before right so we are
still doing inference
as last time but instead of using the
cold inference the cold free energy
we're going to use this you know relaxed
version
for the y equal 23 so if you remember
the y equal 23 was this x
the green x on the right hand side and
then here the free energy was the square
of the distance between the blue x and
the green x right so the
the distance was 0.5 square would would
have been 0.25 and that would have been
the free energy
uh zero temperature zero zero
temperature
limit free energy but in this case we
have now to consider
all these contributions and so i'm gonna
show you
how all those little
z dz will contribute to this free energy
and so we choose a beta equal 1
and we have now this so given that y
prime is going to be this x on the right
hand side
my free energy now comes from the
addition of all these uh terms here the
exponential
of you know minus the energy of
all of this right so all the squares
like the exponential of the negative
squares right
so as you can tell those points that are
close to the
x will have like a
smaller energy and therefore the
exponential will be larger
and that's why you can see them but for
energy that are you know
further away that are very high energy
you do not do the exponential of main
minus and large number you're going to
get basically zero so they don't count
in this summation in this integral okay
first question for people at home
to just check if you are following
how that where does 0.75 come from
so where does this value over here come
from
and you're supposed to type on the chart
such that i can read
aloud what you're saying so i'm asking
once again
where does this value over here 075
come from
and someone is to reply
contribution to the energy yes yes no
the number 075 i i need you to tell me
how to compute 0.75 where does that
number come from
you have all these closest why
till then yeah tell me uh how do i how
do i compute
1 over 2 pi no
x okay x minus beta e okay so how much
is e
e is the square distance right so how
much is it
how much is okay e is 0 25
correct and so e to the minus
0 25 is going to be 0 75
correct okay
so jc got the right answer
good job so great now we know where that
number
comes from so every time you see this
diagram so although it looks very sparse
and pretty and whatever you always have
to pay attention to the number i put on
this
on the screen right so those numbers are
not random number they are
computed by my computer and you always
always always have to check on a piece
of paper
that these numbers make sense because if
they don't make sense
then you're not understanding what's
going on okay so you have to pay
attention
to the numbers and you know
okay i'm a physicist right so you always
i always
uh have in advance in my mind the answer
that my program my
network my whatever is supposed to do
right if i make an electronic circuit i
must understand
i must know in advance what is the you
know voltage somewhere
here and there before i actually measure
it otherwise uh
you know it don't go much ahead
all right all right all right so let's
move on and let's now consider
instead the case for when i have y y
prime
equal 10 right so the 10th item so which
is the
element on the top there so in this case
i'm gonna get that all those points here
will contribute
to the free energy right in this case
we're gonna have a number to 0.26
27 okay someone else that is not jesse
uh can write on the chat how much
where that number comes from so where
does 026 come from
i think you must have understand
understood now
e to the minus 1 kind of yes so
so the distance here is 1.1 1.1 square
is going to be 1.2
and then you take e to the minus 1.2
which is 0 26 yeah
that's correct all right all right all
right okay so
next question uh what happens now
if my y prime is going to be the origin
so what happens if my y prime is the
origin for the zero temperature you're
going to get the
square the distance right from either
side
in this case what's going to be the main
difference if you warm up the
temperature right so you're not zero
temperature it's not
it's not freezing cold we are going to
be increasing a little bit the
temperature
and how is this free energy changing
from
before anyone can type on the chart
it's symmetric yeah that's perfect how
do you know
you already saw the slides before oh you
actually got it right
okay i assume you got it right
all right okay that's perfect yes it's
symmetric right so
uh a point now inside
oh okay yeah i don't know if it's a he
or she
but studied physics in the undergrad
okay cool
all right uh so
in this case you have again that all
those points on the top on the bottom
will contribute to the free energy uh
given that i choose that y
uh y prime to be in the center okay
all right so that's pretty much oh
but why we are talking why are we
talking about this right so we came here
because we had that issue with the
picky picky center right i showed you
before that spinning bathtub
and then the cross-section here that we
had this picky thing
which was coming from the cold free
energy let's
let me show you what happens now if i
choose the warm free energy right
and so if i do that i'm gonna get if i
can scroll my screen
oh you don't see anything okay let me
click click
okay all right and so the red one was
the
super cold the beta is the coldness
again so
large beta is called and then we
reduce the coldness so we increase the
temperature and as you can see the
the picky part becomes smooth smooth
smooth
until it becomes oh
becomes some a parabola with a single
global
minima oh
this is coming out to be remember what
happens if beta goes to zero
you get the average right so you
actually recover the msc
okay i'm just giving like small uh
small like information bits
pills whatever but again yeah so
whenever
we increase the temperature you're going
to be relaxing until you get just one
single minimum
and then there are no more latent
because we just average out everything
without those weights right anyhow
uh i i think now if you if you need to
implement this stuff
in pytorch you're gonna be be getting
like quite frustrated because
they use different names for the things
i just
defined and someone say oh you should
have used their names no
because those are wrong right so i use
the correct name so the one that is
that makes sense i will try to sell it
to you this way
so let me explain to you a little bit of
you know what is the nomenclature i use
uh such that it makes sense at least to
me
otherwise things don't make sense to me
so this is the actual
soft max right not the soft max that
people talk outside this class this is
the actual soft max
which is this you know one over betas
log of blah blah blah some of the
exponentials
i just expanded these um the previous
uh i just expanded the the one over z
i took it out right in the in the
logarithm so i just split the two things
so how do we implement this stuff in
pytorch well you just use this function
which is called torch dot log sum x
which is this soft max actual softmax
right
and then plus or minus that additional
constant over there
right so this is how you want to use how
to implement that
because you know it's numerically stable
moreover if you
this is the actual definition of the
actual soft min
and you can see this is what i wrote
before
you can think about that it's very
similar to the softmax right
the actual softmax what's the only
difference there are two minuses right
and so you can do that you can get get
that away
with you know you put a minus in front
so you cancel the first minus
and you put a minus inside so you cancel
the other minus
and so you know the soft mean is simply
uh you can implement it as a
soft max with the two minuses okay
against actual softmax
and then someone of course is going to
be asking
but what is the softmax we use in class
every time so that one
is actually the soft arc max right
why is that right because a arc max is
going to be like a one hot vector
and d1 tells you what is the index
of the element that has the maximum
value right
so the max gives you retrieves the
maximum value
you know and then the arc max is going
to tell you where is the index
pointing to that maximum value right so
this is like a vector
with a one hot vector and the other one
is a scalar
similarly whenever i compute this soft
max the softer version of the max
now this max is not just the max it's
going to be like a summation of this
uh the logarithm of the summation of the
exponential right
which you can change the temperature if
you get the temperature super cold you
retrieve the max
if you warm up the temperature you get
something like more
like a weighted summation and for the
soft dark max
which was like the arc max is the one
hot if it's super cold
it's gonna still be one hot but if you
warm up the temperature
you're gonna get a distribution
probability distribution right
so whenever someone says oh the soft max
gives you the probability distribution
now that's the soft dark mask okay
uh arc max being the one hot or the zero
temperature limited limit gives you the
one hot
if you increase the temperature you get
a distribution so finally
these are the correct names no one is
using but me
so i hope i didn't create confusion
if i did sorry but still this is the
correct way of seeing these things okay
because it makes sense right so again uh
if you have the
max if you have a function you want to
find the
max it's here right if you have this
function you want to find the mean
you can take the function you flip it
you find the max
and then you flip it back again you get
the mean right so that's what i show you
here
i show you that soft min is simply the
flipped version
the negative right of the max with a
flipped in argument okay
all right all right so enough me talking
about
mathematics and things i hope it was
fine
so this was the part
uh that was concluding the last lesson
right so
this is the end of the inference
and we figured that there is the free
energy
there is a very cold one or there is a
warm
version or there is a very hot version
the hot version is going to be the
average
the warm version is going to be like
something you you may like
is like this marginalization of the of
the latent
and then the super cold version the zero
temperature limit is going to be
this exactly the minimum version minimum
value
uh what i showed you was the fact that
this model is a very poorly trained
model
because those low energy
regions were not you know happening
around this training set right so
let me show you once again uh the same
and the same diagram i showed you
at the beginning of today's lesson which
is this one over here
so here i show you with these white
checks a few
uh samples uh on the
model manifold and then the y's the blue
eyes are the training sample but we
never use the training sample right i
just use the training sample to
compute the energy the free energy but
we never
use them to learn because we didn't talk
about learning we talked about
inference so far right and so
guess what is going to be the next part
of today's lesson
you guessed it right training so now
we're going to be starting
uh to learn how to train learn how to
learn
train train how to learn no learn how to
train
energy based model okay unless there are
questions for me on the chat
no questions everything clear meta
learning yes
no that one is a different subject next
time
all right okay so i think yeah there is
no big deal right so this is just
inference we didn't talk about any crazy
stuff and we talked in for inference
about
about the inference the whole last
lesson so
i guess we can move on move on and start
the training
finding a well-behaved energy function
right
what does this mean so this means we
have to introduce
a loss functional what's a loss
functional
well it's a metric it's a scalar
function
that is telling you how good your
energy function is right so we have an
energy function which is this free
energy
and then we're going to have a function
of my function
which is giving me a scalar which is
just telling me how good this
energy function is right so
a loss functional gives me a scalar
given that i
feed a function
and here i just show to you that if i
have this curly l
as you know the loss functional for the
all the whole batch my whole data set i
can also express this as the average
of these per sample loss functionals
okay so i just do the average of those
per sample those functions
cool so what the heck am i talking about
right so i'm just giving you i'm
making so much hype but i didn't tell
you anything so far
and we already know this stuff from you
know machine learning and you know
previous lessons and so here we go with
the first loss function
which is the which is the energy loss
function
so this energy loss functional
it's simply the free energy
f evaluated in my y
where y is the data point on the data
set right
so whenever whenever we train these
models we're going to be minimizing the
loss functionalities
right the loss function and so in this
case the loss functional
is actually the free energy at the
training point of course right i mean
what this energy function has to do with
the free energy
should be small for data that comes from
the training distribution
large elsewhere right and so what is the
easiest way to do that well of course
we're gonna just have the
loss functional being the free energy
evaluated at the training point
so if it's larger than zero then the
training of the network you know
changing the parameters such that we
minimize the loss functional
is going to be squeezing down the free
energy on those
points right so you have the point you
have a free energy boom
point free energy bomb all right so
we just small like clamp like we
we are reducing the free energy in
correspondence to all these
uh whites why is
there is a check there is a check
because i
want to emphasize the fact that we are
trying to push down
the energy at those locations right so i
push down there is the
arrow pointing down i push down
all right okay i might sound silly but
it doesn't matter i like
myself silly so instead now we're gonna
be introducing these
uh contrastive methods what is a
contrastive method
uh in this case this contrasting method
will have
a white check which is blue why is blue
because it's cold
right so we want to try to get low
energy again the energy the temperature
are connected right
so low energy is going to be cold blue
and then i have a white hot
why is hot why is red why why hot is red
i want to increase the energy right
that's why there is the the hot pointing
upwards and so in this case
uh given that m is a positive number
the difference f of y hat
minus f of y check that the difference
it will the network will try to make it
larger than
m right so for as long as the difference
is smaller than m then these
you know this value over here will have
a
positive value whenever f y hat
minus f y check will be larger than
m then you're gonna have that
you know the output of this stuff is
gonna be zero
okay because there is a a positive part
so
again this hinge loss will simply try to
get
that second difference to be larger than
the
uh the first term the margin
in order to have like a smoother version
of this margin
this is like very binary right if you're
lower than the margin you push
larger than the margin you stop pushing
you can use this other version the
the loss log loss functional
which is a smooth margin uh
you can you can see right whenever you
have that
inside these in this parenthesis you
have a very
negative number so if this is very very
large and this is zero
let's say you're gonna have the x of a
very negative number which is roughly
zero
and i have the log of one which is you
know stop pushing
there is no more instead if this value
here is large
and this value is maybe negative or
whatever is zero
you're gonna have the exponential of
this number which is gonna be very large
and then you're gonna have the one plus
this exponential
uh which again the one gets neglected
you don't get
the log of this x but you're gonna get
basically the uh the
the loss is gonna be proportional to the
energy right if it's very large
cool cool but again for our case uh
we just have a very tiny one-dimensional
latent
so we don't need to do this uh this
contrastive sampling
uh contrastive learning it's necessary
whenever you have like a
um you know maybe like a high
dimensional latent
and so on um so let's just
you know let's just train this model
because i didn't train this model so far
with this energy loss functional
okay and so i train this model it takes
one epoch to converge
it's ridiculously fast okay but it's a
toy example so you understand that
and i'm gonna start by uh showing you
the
zero temperature limit the super cold
free energy okay
uh on the left hand side i'm gonna show
you the untrained version which is the
one we already saw before
so in this case for every training
point the blue point i have a
corresponding
x which is the location on the model
manifold that is the closest to that
training point okay whenever i train
i'm gonna be you know uh get a gradient
that gradient is gonna be i just i told
you before
if you if you get the mean you're gonna
get one item and then if you do the
derivative you're gonna get the
argument which is just the one in
correspondence to the
lowest value and so that one is going to
be represented here
by uh that
arrow over here right so this arrow here
is going to be
the energy the derivative of the energy
which is going to be
just the distance like the y minus
y check and then that's going to be
multiplied by
you know the one in corresponding to the
location that is closest to uh
to our point all right so
what this means is that during training
whenever we use the ztl the zero
temperature limit you're gonna get
the location on the manifold that is
closest to your training point
and then you're gonna get this point to
be moving there
you have this training point you get
this location that is on the manifold
closer to this point
and then you get a gradient that is
making going up here
same you have a training point here
close this point to the manifold here
you get this point a gradient that goes
down here
okay so this is the training procedure
when using this zero temperature limit
one epoch later
on the right hand side the train version
bam
all those axes automatically managed to
arrive to destination finished
so this is like a well-trained model
which i'll show you
where i show you the energy uh going to
zero in
in the all around like acro
corresponding to all the locations
corresponding to my training data set
right the training points the
the blue points what happens if you
have two closest point on a manifold if
for example if y is at zero zero
um
right so in the energy in the in the
zero temperature limit you're going to
get just one point it's going to be
pulled there
and this is very prone to overfitting
let's say our z is not just one
dimensional
large it's larger right so instead of
having like a ellipse you're gonna have
like a potato
if you haven't hold on let me finish the
answer if you have a potato
or potato you're gonna get all these
locations on the potato to go
to those training points and so if your
z is a high dimensional latent variable
you end up with a you start with a
potato and you end up with a porcupine
with all those peaks going uh you know
going out and this is basically
overfitting you just memorize the
training
set in our case this doesn't happen
because our latent is one dimensional so
you can't really pull spikes out
of that thing
but nevertheless we may want to figure
out how to deal with this overfitting
uh by using this you know temperature
regularization thing right so before i
show you there was a peak
if there is a zero temperature limit
then if you increase the temperature you
actually smooth out that peak
and so here i'm going to show you uh
then i answer the other question
actually let me see what happens here
how
do we update the energy function is it
parametrized with uh
oh here this is definition from last
time
right so my energy function is this one
right
where so my energy function is my model
which is the square difference between
the locations and because the laden for
the first component and the code of the
latent for the second component so this
is like
this is how e is parametrized right
uh does the learning interpolate between
the points
uh it asked would this algorithm learn
the
mod the whole ellipse or just the blue
points
okay so i'm getting there okay is there
a visualization
for the spikes to talk about when
overfitting yeah getting there as well
all right so we were telling like we
were talking about
how we train this energy function right
so this energy energy function
is going to be this color thing i show
you over here
and this is you know a different
representation it's simply the location
of that
uh violet ellipse
training for the zero temperature zero
temperature limit means you take that
point
of these ellipse you try to pull it up
right how you pull it up
the only two parameters we had in this
model were
w1 and w2 which were con controlling the
x radius and the y radius right so we
had two parameters
and with two parameters we try to fit
all these
y's right and so basically the network
will
like the the training procedure gradient
descent will eventually
try to change the size of this ellipse
such that it
you know expands and they're going to be
matching all those
uh blue dots okay
the spiky thing was i was saying is that
if you have a high dimensional z
like in this case z is one dimension so
you have like one line
like that if that is two dimensional
it's going to be the whole surface right
and so now it's trivial to overfit you
can move anywhere in the plane there is
no more constraint
of living on that line and so we have to
see
how we can avoid overfitting but in this
case it doesn't happen but
you know we can see now that by
increasing the temperature
we no longer pick points individually
so we are using this marginalization
this vision thingy
so on the bottom part is marginalization
on the left hand side i show you how the
training uh works right
so you have that all those locations
contribute
to these you know the gradient
are just the average of those arrows
here so given that we pick
one y that is this green x
over here you get these all these
points on this manifold will contribute
and will be attracted there here before
we have only one point gets pulled up
here we have that all these points get
pulled up right so it's much harder to
overfit something you want to pay
attention here
is that how do i compute the gradient so
the gradient
i'm computing the gradient of this soft
mean
and so automatically we are gonna get a
soft argument right so if you have a max
you do the gradient you're gonna get the
arc max or if you have a mean
the gradient is gonna be the argument
here we have a soft
mean and therefore the gradient is going
to be the soft argument
multiplied by the the derivative of this
energy
and which is going to be simply this
vector right so the energy is the square
distance if you do the derivative you're
going to get the vector which are
here shown in white and then the height
is gonna be uh basically given to you
by the you know the the vector
multiplied
by this soft argument
cool wow that's a lot to take i think
but
it's it's i think it's just great uh
finally i train the last one
and i'm gonna get something like this on
the right hand side
okay so before i show you
the cross-section for the left-hand side
the untrained version i'm going to show
you now the cross-section for this train
version
so the zero temperature limit the super
cold one i'm gonna get this red one with
a spike
and then as you increase the temperature
as you
reduce this beta we're moving up until
you get this you know average
version this parabolic uh blue one right
okay okay okay and so all of this was
about
unsupervised learning right so far we
only have seen
y's where are the x's
and so this is like yesterday night i'm
like okay maybe i don't talk about
supervised learning like i don't
how long is going to take me to now
train a model with the x's and
everything and
i don't want to do it but then
i just change one line of code and
everything just
works so everything we have seen so far
is exactly the same
for the unconditional which is this
unsupervised
learning way and it's gonna
like one line change you're gonna get
the supervised like the self-supervised
the
conditional and so now in the last five
minutes
we're gonna be talking about the
self-supervised learning or the
conditional case
what does this mean so let's get back to
the training data this is my training
data right
we have we try to learn this horn
that is starting with a horizontal mouth
like it's like a closed mouth ah
like that and then it goes like a very
you know tall and narrow and then the
profile
the envelope is exponential right so
here
the the the radius
goes from beta to alpha and in x
in exp like it's multiplied by the
exponential of two times the x
and the other case the goes from alpha
to beta and also it is multiplied by
this
exponential so let's see if we can learn
this stuff and i didn't know if it was
easy or hard i thought it was hard
it was very easy and so untrained model
manifold
so let's give it a look how does my
model look now
so i have a z and since i have control
over z i take
you know zero to two pi to pi excluded
that's why the bracket is flipped
with an interval of pi over 24.
so i get a line on over there i fit this
z on the decoder and then i'm gonna get
my y
tilde which is gonna be moving uh like
going around
ellipses because that's how my network
is routed inside the decoder right
moreover we're gonna have our y's our
observer why is observed
you can see is observed because there is
a shade in that
bubble there in the circle and now we
have a predictor
and the decoder not only takes my latent
z
but also a predictor and the predictor
is fed
with my observed x and since again if i
have control over z
i can simply say it goes from 0 to 1
with 0.02 interval
let me show you how my untrained network
manifold looks right so this is what
this untrained network manifold looks
all right so how do i train this well i
just do the zero temperature limit
uh free energy training so given my
horn as before i take one point one y
point
i find the closest point on my manifold
and then
i try to pull it up i take this other
point i take the closest point
and i put it down there i take this
point over here i take the closest point
and then put it on
i take this point over here on the on
the horn i take the closest point on the
manifold
and i pull it down i do that for one
epoch
only i told you it was very easy to
train this model
and we get actually i had to define
first what is the energy function right
so my energy function
uh in this case is going to be this e of
x y and z
where again those two components uh like
it's going to be the sum of the square
distances
but in this case i have f and g right so
we have a predictor f
which are both of them mapping r to r r2
and then f is going to be a neural net
mapping my input x through a linear
layer and
reload to a eight dimensional hidden
layer
then i go again through another linear
layer and reload another eight
dimensional
hidden layer and then i have my final
linear layer to end up in two dimensions
so i have a four layer
network input two hidden of size eight
and then one output of size two
and then my g function is simply what
allows me to get
this z going in in loops okay
and but then the point now is that these
two components are going to be scaled
by the output of f
so this is my model very very tiny very
tiny model
and i'm going to be training it and then
i show you
the model manifold so again i take the
same
discretization for the znx and this is
how
the training train model manifold looks
it's awesome right i think it's just
great
all right and this one took nothing no
time to train
so how can we move on how
how what do we do next right how do we
move forward from here
so there are a few more ways to scale
this up not to toy example so
so far i've been kind of cheating right
i've been always
uh embedding into d decoder the fact
that my
z goes around circles but i don't know
that
right so we don't know that and so we
may use something like this
in this case my g function takes my
f and z
and then you know g can be a neural net
as well and
in this case i have to learn the fact
that this stuff
moves around circles so i in this case i
should be learning this sine and cosine
but then how do i know that actually
z is one dimensional well i know because
i generated my data right so
i am the owner of my data generation
process so i knew that
uh theta was a one-dimensional item so
definitely i can just use a latent that
is one-dimensional but
no one can tell me that for you know
natural images or whatever right so
that's the other big issue and so how
how would we deal with the fact that we
don't know
what is the correct size of my latent
uh because again if you choose a large
latent you're going to be
very easily overfitting everything and
so in this case
what changes from the previous slide
which is this one is that now z
is a vector okay so z is a vector
no longer just a single line so actually
this should be a vector and this should
be like whatever
the shape and now my g goes from
the dimension of f and you know
cartesian product with the dimension of
set
into r2 now the issue is that
we need to regularize
this loss functional because otherwise
you are going to be drastically over
fitting right
and so this is what current research
with jan
uh is now what me and my students are
doing
with jan we are trying to figure out
ways to regularize the latent variable
such that we can you know make things
actually not
simply overfit and that was it
that was all i had to tell you about
latent variable
energy-based models inference training
zero temperature limit a bit warmer than
free energy
uh and then we saw the unconditional
case
with unsupervised learning and then we
have seen the conditional case with the
uh self-supervised learning right where
we have access to these
acts and the code to train
these two models uh like the code that i
use for training the conditional case
it's just the same code as i use for the
unsupervised in a supervised case but
with one line change so
really really it doesn't take much
effort to put this together
what it took some effort was to draw
the slides but again that's just because
i like making things pretty
and that was it ah
thank you for listening questions please
go on i mean it's done right class is
finished
you can ask anything you want
are you still awake
yes okay someone is awake can you
explain the input dimension of
g again yes i can explain as much as you
want as you want so now it's office
hours right
you can ask anything you want uh hold on
first question so can you explain the
input dimension of g
uh in this case let me go back to the
first case
in this case g is 1 because it was
fed with z right and then the output was
this g1 and g2 which were cosine and
sine
in the second case g is going to be the
input is going to be this
f which we don't know exactly the
dimension can be anything
so the dimension of f and then
that given that i know that z is one
dimensional
finally which is the super you know norm
like
the actual case that the more realistic
case
is this one where we don't necessarily
know what is
the supposed the dimension for the
latent
and therefore now we're going to use a
whatever dimensional variable latent
variable but
it's going to be necessary to regularize
the
loss functional otherwise as i was
pointing out you can easily overfit
by using that zero temperature limit
uh nevertheless you can use you can warm
up the the temperature
and use that as a regularizer of course
right
did you get it uh yeah
so next question how does this look
without a latent variable
okay without a latent variable it's
exactly as turning
beta to zero okay
so beta to zero you just average
over all possible values how
does what does happen what what are you
going to be ending up having
if you start here on the left side and
then
instead of having all these arrows that
are shaped
now like that all these arrows will have
the same
length well actually these points over
here will be even longer now because
they are further away
so these ellipse will be pulled
in every direction and the way to
minimize this energy
is actually to make it collapse in a
single point
center in zero and so that's the actual
it's a very good question right so what
is the classical
failure mode in you know neural network
whenever you have multiple targets
associated to the same input
you end up predicting the average of all
the possible targets
in this case the average of all possible
targets that are all those
points in the ellipse is going to be
just the point in the origin
which is like the collapse of your model
right so that's a very good question and
the point is that
if you try to learn multi modal output
multimodal data set a data with
a msc like without latent with zero
zero beta infinite temperature you're
just you know
collapsing uh to the mean
the average right m e a and not m i n
mean
average all right another question
uh to be clear at the zero temperature
limit the loss
is only considering the energy
of the nearest point yeah
and as we warm it up the loss is using
a weighted sum of all points and yes
and the weighting weights that you're
using for the weight of the sum
is the are the weights that are coming
from the uh
soft argument right if you take the arg
softening
you have soft mean of the energy right
so that's what you get
you have the soft mean of the energy
right so the f tilde it's soft mean of
the energy
you take the derivative of the softmin
you get the
what you get you get the exponential
divided by the sum of exponential
so that's the soft argument right
multiply
by e prime what is e prime e
was the square distance so if you take
the derivative of the square distance
you just get
the vector which is now multiplied by
this soft argument
so exactly what you said uh which is
very good
summary i'm gonna just read it again and
i show the other chart
so i just read your comment
to be clear at the zero temperature
limit the loss is only considering the
energy of the nearest point
the distance the square distance to the
closest point yeah
and as you warm it up the loss is going
to be the weighted sum
of not the points right what is sum uh
of all those um contributions right
the x uh this exponential of the minus
beta e
right that's what that was written here
on the top right
so as you warm it up you're going to get
this exponential which is the soft mean
so soft mean and then if you compute the
uh
the derivative you're going to get the
soft argument multiplied by the
derivative of the energy
which are the arrows multiplied by the
soft argument so cool
what happens if we allow z to move
freely into the space
we're going to basically get a collapsed
network this model can simply output
zero everywhere
and that's where you may need to use the
contrastive
uh cases right so in that case uh you
know a very easy way to get
zero energy is gonna be just everything
zero right uh but in this in the
in this case you can use the contrastive
case you can say oh no in this case it
should be larger than some margin
and so that's how you can deal with this
larger than uh
like z into d okay so
taking beta okay so taking beta uh to
zero
would defeat the purpose of having a
latent variable at all that's exactly
yeah
and so this is what i kind of briefly
show you i didn't talk about
but this is like a a quick uh derivation
by showing you that if you go beta
equals zero like the limit for beta that
tends to zero
you retrieve the average across all the
latent
and that's basically the you end up with
having msc right
you end up throwing away all those kind
of uh the goodies
right and that was pretty much it
how can you get more out of this lesson
firstly comprehension
if anything was not clear ask me
anything in the comment section below
if you would like to follow up with the
latest news follow me on twitter
under the endl alph cnz
if you would like to be notified when i
upload the latest video
don't forget to subscribe to the channel
and turn on the notification bell
and if you like this video don't forget
to put a thumb up
this video has a transcript in english
and if you would like to contribute to
the translation in your language
please let me know so here as you can
see we have the
write up where we can see all these
video that has been transcribed here in
plain english
and then again as i said before if we go
back to the homepage
we can see here in the english flag and
we can select different languages
now we have arabic spanish version
french italian japanese
korean russian turkish and chinese and
your language is just
waiting for you to be translated in
finally
do play with notebook and by torch in
order to get yourself
more acquainted with all these new
topics
and then if you find any typo or
mistakes or anything just please let me
know
directly on github or if you feel brave
enough you can even send a pull request
it will be gladly appreciated thank you
for listening and don't forget to like
share and subscribe
bye